Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan and this time
we're going to be looking at the
difference between polar bonds which
we talked about in our last video on
electronegativity and a polar molecule.
Now The big difference between these is
that a polar bond does not always tell
you that a molecule, which has multiple
atoms, is going to always be polar.
And a lot of it has to feed into its
vesper geometry, or its structure,
or molecular shape, that we talked
about in a previous video as well.
So, this is something that...
That takes a lot of different concepts
that we've started to slowly build
together and combine them together.
So this is where it takes a lot
of little things to think about to
be able to see the whole picture.
So what this kind of looks like
is almost like this picture
over here that I found online.
So if you have like a little
water molecule, you can
see the oxygen is really.
pulling on both these hydrogens
and it is very similar to what
this electronegativity picture is.
So for example, if I looked at just
the OH bond and we were to look at
that from last time, well, we could say
that, okay, oxygen has a value of 3.
5 and hydrogen has a value of 2.
1.
So if we take that difference,
then we'll quickly see that, oh, 3.
5 minus 2.
1.
Well, that is a 1.
4 difference.
So it's going to be
polar now, but OH isn't.
Just a molecule, right?
It's just a one bond.
So if I kind of complete this Structure
and let's say I do it for water.
Well water looks something like this
right where we have O It is bound to a
hydrogen on both sides and it has two
lone pairs So this is a bent geometry.
So how does that get affected by polarity?
Well the same picture happens.
Um, what we're trying to see is, is
there a buildup of electrons on one
side of the molecule versus another?
So if I have the same picture, I have a 3.
5 on oxygen, a 2.
1 on each of these hydrogens, well,
we can go through our labeling process
to show that, oh, the difference
between both of these bonds is 1.
4.
So how can we illustrate that?
Well, let's redraw our water.
So the first way is just using
the little Delta, the little delta
symbols that we went over last time.
So if I take a delta negative, which for
being that oxygen is more, has a higher
value that makes it a delta negative
and each hydrogen is going to have a
delta plus telling you that the un.
Evenness of this molecule is going to
be more in favor of the oxygen of this
molecule So that's the ultimate idea
here is that more of it is going to be
on the oxygen So we can also show the
general direction of this dipole as well
So the way we can do that as well is if
I take the oxygen again and with the two
hydrogens And I draw my little dots here.
Well, we can show that the overall change
of this is going from a positive side on
the bottom and pointing up towards the
oxygens in an overall negative direction.
You can also, depending on who your
teacher is, or who is kind of going over
all this with you, they might have you do
it where each, you draw this on each bond
as well, pointing towards the oxygens.
So, it could be an overall, which
is in blue, or you could do just
the individual bonds as well.
And both are, both are correct.
Um, it just depends on, realistically,
who you're taking this with,
and how you are looking at that.
So, you have the individual dipole,
So we can represent it that way.
So what this is telling you
is that being that there is an
overall positive on one part of the
molecule, this is an uneven molecule.
Meaning that no matter how I kind of
look at it, there isn't There isn't
just pull in one direction or another.
It's all built up on that oxygen.
So when it's all built like that, so
if I kind of go back and draw my little
orbital picture that I had earlier in
the previous video, being that oxygen is
delta negative and the hydrogens are delta
plus, more of that is going to be built.
Onto the oxygen side of the molecule where
not as much of it's going to be seen on
this side So the seesaw is pushing toward
is on the oxygen side or the tug of war is
on the oxygen as well So this is the basic
idea looking at this even farther This
can get a little complicated depending
on which geometry we have at hand because
if we're thinking of a tug of war Can
geometry play a role to cancel out poles?
Meaning that molecules are polar if the
polar bonds, they got to work together
Meaning it has to cause a pile up.
So like with water up here, we had a pile
up on one side So what we have to see here
is we're gonna assume the following So
what I'm assuming is that I have a bond
AB and that B is more electronegative
than So, if I have certain geometries,
these can lead to non polar molecules.
Meaning that, if I had, let's
say if I start with the ones
that we were looking at before.
So I had the bent geometry, so
this one is like water for example.
We can see that, With this one, there
is an overall net dipole, being that I
made it so that the B's are more polar.
So they're pulling away
from that central atom.
It's all going in the same direction.
All the arrows are pointing away.
They're all pointing down.
This is polar, being that
there is a net dipole.
So that overall downwardness from the
whole entire thing is, it's all down.
Now when I have A non polar
molecule, these are what I
refer to as basic geometries.
Meaning that they have the same atom.
Nolone pairs, so nolone pairs, and the
same atoms around the central atom.
So what's gonna happen, so if I take this
first example, like BAB, this is like,
both of the B's are pulling in opposite
directions, and they're of equal strength.
So a good example of this would be, is
something that is a linear geometry.
So if I take something like CO2, for
example, And I try to draw this one.
So let's draw this in another location.
So let's have CO2.
And I look at the
electronegativity differences.
Well, oxygen was a value of 3.
5.
That's on both sides.
Hydrogen was a, or not hydrogen,
carbon was a value of 2.
0.
So what this is telling you is that the
overall pull in both directions is 1.
0.
And, they're both pulling in complete
opposite directions, so one is 1.
0, the other is 1.
0.
So as a result, they're going to cancel.
So it's like playing tug of war with
yourself, in a, in a sense, because
they're pulling on the central atom.
So if I have a little knot in the middle.
And oxygen is pooling on one
side, and I have another oxygen
pooling on the other side.
They can pool all day, all night, but
as a result, they aren't going to go
anywhere, even if they keep pooling.
So, when we have anything that
has a central atom with no lone
pairs, and it's bound to the same
atoms, it's going to be nonpolar.
So if we look at all these ones in
the first column that are here, so
whether it's linear, trigonal planar,
tetrahedral, trigonal bipyramidal,
octahedral, all of these are capable of
being nonpolar because of an even pooling.
So that's what we're looking for.
Are they even?
And that's, so if I go through another
example, let's say if I have CF4.
So fluorine, as we know, is one of the
most electronegative atoms possible.
Fluorine has a value of 4.
0.
Carbon is 2.
5.
So as a carbon fluorine bond, this is 4.
0 minus 2.
5.
That is 1.
This is definitely a polar bond.
We cannot deny that.
However, what happens if we put
it together in its geometry?
Well, being that we have,
carbon can bond to four things.
So it's going to make
a tetrahedral geometry.
Because there's no lone pairs on carbon,
so when we draw that, we're gonna have C,
another F,
just like so, and we can have that
where, alright, well, delta, we can
have delta negatives on all sides,
and there is a little delta positive
on the carbon, but as a result,
these are pulling in equidistance
and equal angles from each other.
So, being that this is an equal
pulling, the dipoles cancel.
So, this molecule, yes,
it has polar bonds.
In fact, it has four polar bonds.
However, this is a non polar
molecule because of the tug of war.
So, just like this one from above
with CO2, this has two polar bonds.
There's no denying that
CO is a polar bond.
However, it is a non polar
molecule due to the geometry.
Let's try another one.
Let's see if it's going
to be polar or non polar.
What if I give you NH3?
Would this be something that's polar?
So, we have to first determine
what's a central atom.
So the central atom in this case
is going to be what can bond,
what can make more friends.
So if you remember from my previous video,
nitrogen can make up to three friends.
So, nitrogen is going
to be our central atom.
It has five valence electrons, and
as a result, we're going to put our
hydrogens on each side just like this.
So, now let's label all
of the electronegativity.
Hydrogen had a value of 2.
1.
Nitrogen has a value of 3.
0.
That's right here.
So 3.
0 minus 2.
1.
That's going to be very polar covalent.
It's going to fit in that
little range of ours.
So let's write that down for ourselves.
The 3.
0, 2.
1, 2.
1.
We can, we can copy and
paste this molecule.
So we have in a couple of places.
So as a result, This is going to
be very much distributed all over
the molecule, these, these charges.
We can see that it doesn't
seem to be pretty even, but we
gotta determine the geometry.
So being that we have four groups
around it, one of them is a lone pair.
So this is gonna be trigonal pyramidal.
If you're not sure about that, we
can look at our little chart here.
So we have one lone pair,
four groups, that goes down
to here, trigonal pyramidal.
So it's pulling in our vesper structures.
There's a lot of stuff we gotta do.
So our HS are gonna be pointing down like
an, like an upside down, like an umbrella.
So what that's telling you is that
okay, the overall positive side
of it is on the bottom and it's
all pointing up towards nitrogen.
So is this polar or nonpolar?
In this case it's polar, right?
More of it is on the nitrogen or
is on the um, nitrogen versus.
Another one.
What, so another thing to
keep in mind is we've got to
look at overall molecules too.
We got to look at big molecules, try
to see is the overall thing polar.
So let's do maybe one
last example together.
What if I give you something like ethanol?
So ethanol is, the
structure of this is CH3
Oh, CH3CH2OH.
This is where it comes to understanding
how are molecules situated, how we can
predict geometries on a bigger molecule.
A lot of these types of molecules
are written how they are bound to
each other, meaning that if we can.
Identify all the central atoms.
What can make multiple bonds?
We can quickly see what the geometry is.
So for carbon, right?
Carbon can bond to four things.
Oxygen can bond to two.
So you can quickly kind of see like, all
right, well, what is the geometry here?
So each of the carbons are going to
have very much a tetrahedral shape.
around each of those hydrogens that
are being showcased, just like so.
And then the oxygen is going to
be making two bonds, one with the
carbon, one with the hydrogen.
So, is this polar or non polar?
Well, it gets a little tricky.
We got to look at the
different regions of it.
So for this one, one thing is, is that
there's specific bonds that are always
polar and always have that trend.
So one, you can see that
there's oxygen and hydrogen.
This is a very polar bond.
Oxygen has a 3.
5, hydrogen is 2.
1, that area is polar, which tells you
that, okay, this is a polar molecule.
However, this region is very nonpolar.
So, why is this region nonpolar?
Well, with CH bonds, CH is just 2.
5 and 2.
1.
It's a difference of 0.
4.
It's not much.
Carbon carbon, we did that last time.
That's a difference of zero
because they're the same bond.
So, we have a polar.
In a nonpolar region.
So with that, it's going to lead to
different intermolecular forces, which is
what you're going to cover soon, or we're
going to cover in a future video together.
Um, it's something that it
leads to different interactions
and different trends.
So there's a couple of bonds
that can help you decide, is this
going to be a polar molecule?
So if you see like the following,
so if you see like HF, uh, HN,
These are always usually polar.
You see, uh, C H.
This is nonpolar.
Uh, if you see things that are like, uh, C
O, C N These ones are polar, so these are
some of the little different trends that
you're going to look for in molecules.
So this little list might
help you to be able to quickly
identify polar, non polar trends.
I hope this video helped a little bit
to be able to figure out polarity.
It can get a little tricky, the more
you practice the easier it will get,
um, and look out for my future video
on intermolecular forces so you can see
how do different polar molecules, how
do they interact with each other when
you're looking at these different bonds.
Alright, well thank you and I hope
you have a wonderful day and please
hit that subscribe button so I
hope to see you back in the future.
Alright, bye now.